<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Beryl]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Beryl]]></description>
        <link>https://thegrid.ai/beryl/</link>
        <generator>The Grid</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2015 14:58:55 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://thegrid.ai/beryl/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fraser Institute Study]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<h1>Fraser Institute Study</h1>]]></description>
            <link>https://thegrid.ai/beryl/fraser-institute-study/index.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">1619e637-cec6-4bb8-9e28-12ea894bee63</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2015 14:57:49 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[No title]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>The image is from the Alberta tar sands.   The recent piece published by the Fraser Institute is a high-pressure sales-pitch, attempting to prompt impulsive decision-making from our government to accelerate approval for the LNG project in our province. Or in other words, to ignore the range of potential costs from the venture, and the concerns of all the stakeholders, while companies come into our home and destroy its ecological integrity. I have three concerns with how the authors approached the study. As they quoted Milton Friedman in their opening, in the spirit of economic debate, I’ll quote an economist of my own:  Adam Smith: "The proposal of any new law or regulation of commerce which comes from this order, ought always to be listened with great precaution, and ought never to be adopted till after having been long and carefully examined, not only with the most scrupulous but with the most suspicious attention. It comes from an order of men, whose interest is never exactly the same with that of the public, who have generally an interest to deceive and even oppress the public, and who accordingly have, upon many occasions, both deceived and oppressed it." (Smith, 1776)  Concern 1 [Biased Volume Estimates]  The data provided that forms the foundation of the ‘capacity/consumption model’ are all from pro-industry sources. The Oil & Gas Commission and the Canada Association of Petroleum producers both advocate for the pipeline project. The National Energy Board was just criticised in August 2015 for appointing a full-time board position to Steven J. Kelly, who was a paid Kinder Morgan consultant. Quoting former CEO of BC Hydro, Marc Eliesen:  “It’s utterly incredible the Government of Canada would appoint such an industry consultant to a regulatory agency that presumably is interested in the public interest, and not the interest of multinational oil corporations … the NEB have become totally become a captured industry regulator” (National Observer, 2015). The paper also sources data from BP – the petroleum producer, who has long-term contractual relationships with Kinder Morgan (BP, 2012). Acquiring consumption projections from only pro-LNG project sources is likely to result in an inflated, engineered number! A summary of their production/consumption figures:  Domestic Production (+85%), Domestic Consumption (-27.6%) between 2000 - 2014. APAC Production (+70.4%), APAC Consumption (+48.3%), Excess Capacity (+141%), between 2015 - 2035. This is production excluding that of BC. If the paper is accurate that the “10 BC projects combined would be the largest among the five top exporters, with a 3rd of total export capacity”, and production from current suppliers is as projected, global supply will increase by even more than a third of current levels with significant downward pressure on prices in a supply-side shock.  Concern 2 [Profitability Estimates]   First Mover Advantage  The paper tries to “provide reasonable economic benefits to shortening policy time” as any further delay will cost “BC Billions”. If the project is that sensitive and market conditions so competitive that it will be so much “less remunerative due to delays”, is it really sustainable in the long term? It states: “the longer it takes for Canadian projects to move forward, the more likely ... [we] will be displaced by these other projects … it’s difficult to overstate the importance of acting before the equivalent market share is acquired by [competitors]”. The assumption that we can defend our position once we have a certain market share, although we do not have a cost-advantage, is ridiculous.  Industry  Commodities are a very capital intensive industry: “most of the cost of producing LNG is capital cost of facilities”. Classic for highly operational leveraged firms, there will be incentive to drive down unit costs and compete on price for volume sales – not quality. OPEC recently drove down the market price of crude to displace less efficient American shale producers and maintain their market share - with some success as many were too highly financially leveraged (Financial Times, 2015).   We're not even as cost-efficient as our American counterparts with production or delivery to APAC, "the important market". How can we compete in this cost-driven commodity industry without future government support! There are no "Rolls Royce" of LNG - we certainly cannot command a premium on price.   Concern 3 [Cost Ommissions]  Costs such as the societal and environmental costs – among others, that discuss the negative externalities of this project (ie. emissions, ecological damage, etc) are ignored. “Revenues above social costs of producing are economic costs [of delay]”. I agree with that statement. However, the paper omits these costs and only assumes that "most of the costs of producing LNG is in the capital cost of facilities". It assesses a full range of benefits but ignores a full range of costs. GIBO – Garbage in, Garbage out.  The paper mentions substantial job creation for our province. Yet, these newly created jobs might pull capable people from other industries that could have otherwise been spending their mental and physical capacity in an alternative productive form. Again, another quote from Adam Smith:  "Entrepreneurs will have to pay more to attract workers from established trades into new ones. Employment in new trade may be seen as less secure, or more dependent on the fickleness of fashion" (Smith, 1776).  The "pay more to attract" can refer to the premium in excess of the opportunity cost of displaced labor. The "fickleness of fashion" refers to whether future demand in LNG can be accurately forecasted. (no, it can't). We should look at the costs from a societal perspective as it is borne by all, not from a private project evaluation where costs are significantly understated. The paper states that "investors will put their own resources at risk, and thus have efficient incentives to balance economic returns with inevitable risks and uncertainties" – but these are not their resources. These are the resources of the public.  The $5.5b CAD in benefits, the conservative estimate of lost revenues from delays, ignores these peripheral costs.   Conclusion  Just because we are lucky enough to have a natural resource endowment doesn’t mean we have to use them. Nobel Laureate Joseph E. Stiglitz highlights a small country named Mauritius which has no exploitable natural resource but still can provide free education, transport, healthcare to it's citizens (Stiglitz, J. 2011). They invest in their people and their community.  The paper argues that it’s "the job of governments to impose appropriate environmental, safety, and other controls protecting community interests in an expeditious manner.” I agree up to the point of “in an expeditious manner”. According to John Locke, governments are given power to govern by people. Their duty is towards society and if they fail to promote public good and to protect the rights of people, they should be replaced (Locke, 1690).  For all the trend of corporate social responsibility, the goal of the private sector is to create profit by free enterprise. It’s not reasonable for us to expect them to focus on the negative externalities of their actions. However, it is reasonable for us to be angry when they actively try to manipulate the rules and mislead the common citizen.  If I'm wrong anywhere, please correct me. I'm new at this. I just have not felt so agitated reading something in a while.    The original source article from the Fraser Institute here: http://www.fraserinstitute.org/studies/lng-exports-from-british-columbia-the-cost-of-regulatory-delay  http://www.nationalobserver.com/2015/08/01/news/harper-gov%E2%80%99t-appoints-kinder-morgan-consultant-neb  http://www.bp.com/en/global/corporate/press/press-releases/kinder-morgan-and-bp-north-america-enter-into-long-term-agreements.html  Smith, A. (1776). The wealth of nations, Book I, Chapter XI, Conclusions of the chapter, p.267, para.10  Hayek, F.A (1963). The market and other orders, Chapter: The economy, science, and politics.  http://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/the-mauritius-miracle  Locke, J. (1690). Two treatises of government.  http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/0/5974a3ce-52e0-11e5-b029-b9d50a74fd14.html</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://thegrid.ai/beryl/the-image-is-from-the-alberta-tar-sands-the-recent-piece/index.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">f55b7d29-5652-4782-902d-8c155f0ce787</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2015 14:55:15 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>